<resources>
    <!-- Dialogs messages -->
    <string name="dialog_btn_accept">Accept</string>
    <string name="dialog_btn_cancel">Cancel</string>
    <string name="warning_live_mute_title">Attention!</string>
    <string name="warning_live_mute_msg">MUTE YOUR DEVICE.   The device must remain silent during the representation. Thank you very much for your consideration.</string>
    <string name="warning_no_listen_title">Attention!</string>
    <string name="warning_no_listen_msg">Option not available on representation days. We apologize for the inconvenience</string>
    <string name="dialog_download_title">Important Info</string>
    <string name="dialog_download_msg">Downloading audio content for this section is required. Only be downloaded once. We recommend a WiFi network connection.</string>
    <string name="progressdialog_download_title">Info</string>
    <string name="progressdialog_download_msg">Downloading audio content&#8230;\nThis process may take a while.</string>
    <string name="progressdialog_unzip_title">Info</string>
    <string name="progressdialog_unzip_msg">Preparing audio content&#8230;</string>
    <string name="alert_unzip_error_title">Error preparing audio</string>
    <string name="alert_unzip_error_msg">Error preparing audio.\nPlease try again.</string>
    <string name="alert_remotedbmanager_error_title">Error</string>
    <string name="alert_remotedbmanager_error_msg">Error receiving data. Maybe caused by a unstable internet connection.\nPlease, review it.</string>
    <string name="alert_audio_notfound_error_title">Error</string>
    <string name="alert_audio_notfound_error_msg">Audio not found, you probably were disconnected while downloading. We recommend to erase the app data from the settings menu.</string>
    
    <!-- Menu activity-->
    <string name="btn_language">English</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_live_title">Follow Live</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_live_subtitle">Follow the representation live</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_listen_title">Listent El Misteri</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_listen_subtitle">Follow La Festa manually</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_info_title">Info and History</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_info_subtitle">Learn all about the representation</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_tickets_title">Buy tickets</string>
    <string name="btn_menu_tickets_subtitle">Ticketing Service</string>
    
    
    <!-- Menu option 1. Live activities-->
    <string name="cast">Cast</string>
    <string name="today_cast"> Starring in today\'s representation:</string>
    <!--string name="live">En directo DE</string-->   
    
    <!-- Menu option 2. Scene player activities-->
    <!-- Scene menu -->
    <string name="scenes">Scenes selection</string>    
    
    <!-- Menu option 3. Information and history activities-->
    <string name="info">Info</string>
    <string name="info_history_title">History</string>
    <string name="info_history_subtitle">The origin of Misteri d\'Elx</string>
    <string name="info_history_longtext">The origin of the Mystery of Elche has not yet been exactly determined due to a lack of accuracy in the documents. Two local traditions exist regarding its birth. One of them links the Festa with the conquest of the Muslim Elche by the Aragonese troops of James I of Aragon, in 1265, that’s to say, with the birth of the village to Christian civilization. Another legendary tradition tries to give the birth of the Mystery a miraculous origin, relating it to the apparition or “Coming” of the image of the Virgin of Elche on December 29th 1370. In this way the consueta (libretto or festival book) of the Festa would have been found, next to the figure of Mary, inside a wooden ark floating on the waters of the Mediterranean Sea, in the nearby Tamarit Beach (in nowadays Santa Pola), by the soldier and coastguard Francesc Cantó. \n\n
		Nevertheless, the latest research, both on the Elche’s play itself, and on medieval European theatre in general, agree to date The Mystery of Elche to the second half of the 15th century ( when a peak in theatre with an Assumptionist subject is detected) as the most likely. \n\n
		If we make a short overview of the historic documentation of the play, we find out that, in its beginnings, it was organized by some families of the local small nobility, like the Perpinyàs or the Caros. The oldest documental reference of the Festa we have been able to trace to the present day dates back to the deeds of a woman from Elche, Isabel Caro, in 1523. In her last will she leaves an amount of money to continue a “great feast and solemnity” that religious people of the village celebrated in the church of Saint Mary during the festivity of the Assumption of the Mother of God, in honor of a figure of the Virgin that the testatrix had in her house and that, after her death, should remain in the hermit of Saint Sebastian. \n\n
		We have news of the existence in the village in 1530 of the Brotherhood of Our Lady of the Assumption, which had it seed in the cited hermit of Saint Sebastian. This Brotherhood was in charge of preparing the festivity. The Brotherhood was led by some treasurers and butlers and, besides the contributions of brothers and the alms received, it had an annual income from the municipal Council. \n\n
		However, the lack of funds and of persons willing to lead the Brotherhood put the Mystery of Elche in a serious danger in the last years of the 16th century. It was in 1609 when, at last, the Council of the village agreed to take in charge the organization and financing of the Festa. In order to do so, a serious of municipal taxes, like those on grain milling and the selling of meat were established. In this way, it should be pointed out that there existed in the city an administration called the “gallon of oil”, which received an alms dedicated to the Virgin, consisting in a gallon of oil for every caldron of oil that the important soap making industry of Elche boiled (centuries 16th to 17th). The profits of that administration were mainly destined to the keeping of the stage machinery and paying musicians and singers. \n\n
		But, once again, in the first third of the 17th century the Mystery was in danger of disappearing. This time, it was the bishopric of Orihuela that, following the rules of Trento, tried to prohibit the representation because it was held inside a church. The Council of Elche pleaded before the Royal Court of Valencia and, in 1632, managed to get Pope Urban VIII to sign a Rescript granting the privilege allowing the representation of The Mystery of Elche inside the temple of Saint Mary forever. \n\n
		This was not the only clash to be held between ecclesiastical and civil authorities around the organization of the Festa. In the 1700s ( due to a matter of exemption of local taxes for the religious) and in 1734 ( due to a quarrel about the appointment of the chapel Master ) the frictions between both institutions raged up in an alarming way although, in the end, the rights of the Council prevailed, based on the historic customs and traditions preserved in the city. \n\n
		In the last years of the 18th century(with the prohibition of the scene of the Judiada due to the many incidents it created) and in the first years of the 20th century (with the suppression of Elche’s musical chapel) the Mystery entered a period of a clear artistic decadence. This decadence became more pronounced in the last third of the 19th century, both for lack of economic resources dedicated to the play, and for the scarce interest that the inhabitants of Elche, political authorities included, granted it. \n\n
		Thanks to an awareness campaign led in the city by Pere Ibarra y Ruiz, chronicler and scholar, in 1924 the “Protecting Board of the Festa de Elche” was created. This made possible a staging and musical revision of the play. The score was revised by Oscar Esplá, a musician from Alicante, who set up again the scene of the Judiada, amongst other things. This renaissance period recovered part of the past splendor of the play and had its culmination in 1931, when the Government of the II Republic granted it the title of National Monument. The protection of the state organized its links to the National Board of Music and Lyrical Theatres (directed by the above mentioned Esplá ) by means of a primitive local Trust. \n\n
		After the Civil War (1936&#8211;1939), the so called National Board for the Restoration of The Mystery of Elche and its Temples was created. The main mission of this Board was the reconstruction of the church of Saint Mary(burnt down in February 1936) as well as the setting up of the representations of the Mystery, suspended during the war. Once the restoring tasks ended, in 1948, the local Trust was transformed into the National Board of the Mystery of Elche, and after the passing of the Act of the Mystery d’Elx by the regional authorities in December 2005, it became what nowadays is the Board of the Misteri d’Elx. This board has the mission of organizing the assumptionist play. It is backed economically and institutionally by several governmental organizations like the Valencian Regional Government, Elche’s City Council and Alicante’s Provincial Govermnent. \n\n
    </string>
    <string name="info_text_title">Text</string>
    <string name="info_text_subtitle">The lirerary text of El Misteri</string>
    <string name="info_text_longtext">The literary text of the Mystery of Elche, written in Valencian&#8211; with a psalm and some verses in Latin&#8211; is relatively short if we compare it with other representations of similar characteristics whose librettos have been preserved to the present day. For example, the assumptionist mystery of Tarragona (14th century) or the play that was held in the Cathedral of Valencia (15th century). The Elche play consists of a total of two hundred and fifty&#8211;nine verses, distributed in different kinds of stanzas. The most abundant are quatrains with lines of eight syllables rhyming in the sequence “aabb”, that’s to say, stanzas of the model known as “noves rimades”. There are also, although to a lesser extent, lines of ten syllables, distributed in quatrains with the rhyming pattern “abab”, and also five line verses rhyming “aabb” and “abab”. \n\n
		The brevity of the text is perhaps due to the lesser importance that the literary part has been granted through history, in comparison to the musical and scenic part. The complexity of some of the chants, with abundant musical ornaments, and the use of spectacular pieces of aerial stage machinery has led to a reduction of part of the verses, in order to keep the representation to a moderate duration. References preserved show that it was in the 17th century when the literary part of the drama was finally established. \n\n
		Literary and musical texts, as well as the stage notes that allow the representation of the play, have been preserved throughout the centuries in manuscripts called consuetas. Although some researchers presume the existence of a primitive consueta belonging to the Brotherhood of Our Lady of the Assumption, that was responsible for the staging of the Mystery until 1609, the first precise reference to one of these librettos doesn’t appear until 1625. It was this year when Honorat Martí de Montsí, a knight of the Holy Office in Orihuela, asked Gaspar Soler Chacón, from Elche, a copy of the text of the Festa, probably so the Inquisition could control whether the play observed orthodoxy. It is the “Llibre de la Festa de Nostra Señora de la Sumptió ditta vulgarment la Festa de la vila de Elig, sacada de son original register a instancia del señor Honorat Martí de Montsí, cavaller familiar del Sant Offisi y Capitá per sa Magestat en la ciutat de Oriola”. \n\n
		Soler Chacón only copied the verses of the chants and the stage notes&#8211;but not the music&#8211; of the official consueta that was kept by the Council of the village in its “three key ark” or safe. That copy might have only been allowed because it was an order of the Inquisition for, as Soler himself pointed out, the Council never authorized any transcriptions of the consueta because of the “solemnity of the Festa”. On the other hand, the manuscript was enriched with a series of historical side notes, referring to the city and the festivals related with the assumptionist drama, that Soler Chacón himself made. The original manuscript of this consueta of 1625 hasn’t been preserved, but we have notice of it thanks to an edition made by the chronicler of Elche, Pere Ibarra i Ruiz (1858&#8211;1934), in 1933. \n\n
		Book of the Festa of our Lady of the Assumption, popularly known as Festa of the village of Elche, extracted from its original text by Honorat Martí de Montsí knight of the Holy Office and Captain of His Majesty in Orihuela. \n\n
		In 1639, an anonymous person&#8211; “a devout person”&#8211; made a new copy of the official manuscript: “Consueta de la Festa de Nostra Señora de la Assuntió, que se celebra en dos actes, vespra y dia, en la insigne vila de Elig. Escrit per un devot seu en VI dies del mes de febrer del any MDCXXXIX”. This time, the music of the chants was included, as well as side notes with the names of the composers who took part in the polyphonic reform of the Mystery in the 16th century. This copy of the consueta is also known by means of a copy, published in a partial edition by the publisher from Murcia Javier Puentes y Ponte (1830&#8211;1903) in 1887. \n\n
		In 1706, the archive of the Council of Elche was laid waste by the Bourbon troops, during the War of the Spanish Succession. During the incident, the original consueta suffered severe damage. Three years later it was copied by the Beneficiary Joseph Lozano y Roiz so it could be used by the chapel Master or musical conductors of the Mystery. The document is titled “Consueta or guide for the great play on the vespers and the day of the Mother of God of the Assumption, Patron of Elche, for chapel Masters (…) written by the beneficiary Joseph Lozano y Roiz, priest, in the year 1709”. This copy written by Lozano&#8211;which includes side notes and both the literary and the musical texts&#8211; is the oldest libretto preserved to the present day. It is, besides, the only one belonging to a public institution: The Municipal Historical Archive of Elche. Two facsimile editions of this consueta have been published: one in 1941, paid for by the Spanish Institute and with a preface written by Eugenio d’Ors, and another one in 1986, published by the Regional Valencian Government, with a prologue written by Francesc Massip and M. Carmen Muntané. \n\n
		Lozano y Roiz himself made another copy of the consueta in 1722, which turned out almost identical to the previous one, although it is untitled. This copy is kept nowadays in the library of the chronicler of the city Juan Orts Román (1898&#8211;1958). In 2002, The Board of the Misteri d’Elx published a facsimile edition of this document, with an introductory study written by the researcher Luis Quirante Santacruz (1959&#8211;2000). \n\n
		The last consueta we have notice of &#8211;from a chronological point of view&#8211; is dated in 1751. It is a copy made by Carlos Tàrrega I Caro from the above mentioned text of 1625. Its title is Llibre de la Festa de Nostra Senyora de la Assumpció, dita vulgarment la Festa de Agost de la vila de Elig, treta de originals registres antichs&#8230; It doesn’t contain, thus, the score of the play, although it includes a serious of notes about events that happened during the representations of the Mystery in the 16th and 17th centuries. These notes are very useful in order to analyze the history and evolution of the assumptionist drama. This consueta is kept in the library of the heirs of the chronicler José M. Ruiz de Lope y Pérez (1831&#8211;1900) and it was published in a facsimile edition in 1992 by Manuel Pastor’s editorial in Elche, with a preliminary study by Joan Castaño. \n\n
		Consueta of the Festa of Our Lady of the Assumption, in two acts, vespers and day, in the illustrious village of Elche. Written by Her devout in six days of the month of February 1639. \n\n
		Book of the Fiesta of Our Lady of the Assumption, popularly known as August Fiesta of the village of Elche, taken from old original records… \n\n
	</string>
       
    <string name="info_music_title">Music</string>
    <string name="info_music_subtitle">About the Misteri chants</string>
    <string name="info_music_longtext">The most outstanding artistic aspect of the Mystery of Elche is the musical one. Elche’s drama is all sung and it contains melodies that, according to the experts, come from different times: there are chants in it with a clear medieval background, a very interesting renaissance influence, and even adornments and insertions from the baroque, and even latter times, can be found in it. However, its musical unity is extraordinary, as different studies and research on this matter have pointed out. Research that has been carried out from the early years of the 20th century by musicologists and scholars such as Felipe Pedrell, Óscar Esplá, Samuel Rubio, Ismael Fernández de la Cuesta, José M. Vives or M. Carmen Gómez Muntané. \n\n
		The chants of the Mystery can be roughly classified in monodic and polyphonic. Really, from the twenty&#8211;six musical pieces we find in the historical consuetas of 1709 and 1722 –with the exception of the psalm In exitu Israel d’Egipto, which is repeated three times in the second act&#8211;, ten are monodic and sixteen polyphonic, although in both cases some of the melodies are repeated with different literary texts. \n\n
		Some of the monodic chants&#8211; more abundant in the first act of the play&#8211; show a clear influence from medieval Gregorian. In fact, the consueta itself remarks that one of the chants of the Virgin Mary must be sung in the tone of the Vexilla Regis, hymn compsed in the 6th century in honour of a fragment of the Cross of Jesus Christ. In the same way, there have been detected certain points of contact between some of the chats of Saint John and Saint Peter and the Gregorian hymn Victimae paschali laudes. This technique consisting in adapting new literary texts to existing scores, religious and popular –known as contrafactum&#8211; was very common in old theatre representations, because, in this way spectators, which were familiar with the original melodies, were soon identified with the staging. In other cases, the abundant melismatic ornamentation of the songs, accumulated through centuries, hinders a clear identification of the original version. The clearest example can be found in the melody of the angel in the cloud or “pomegranate”. \n\n
		There has also been found certain concordance between the polyphonic chants of the Mystery and carols and other songs compiled in the Musical Songbook of Palace. This shows that during the renaissance musical reform the drama underwent in the 16th century, not only original pieces specifically composed for it were added, but also a contrafactum of already known melodies was also added. \n\n
		Thanks to some notes found in the consueta of 1639, we know the name of three of the composers who took an active role in the above mentioned polyphonic reform. They were a certain Ribera, who, with certain precautions, has been identified as Antonio de Ribera, singer of the Pontifical Chapel in Rome between 1513 and 1523. Other scholars, however, think this Ribera was a tenor in the Imperial Chapel of Maximilian II of Austria between 1566 and 1567. \n\n
		Another of the authors we know of the polyphony of the Festa is the canon Pérez, identified by the experts as Ginés Pérez (1548&#8211;1600), chapel maestro of the cathedral of Valencia and canon in the cathedral of Orihuela. \n\n
		Finally, Lluís Vich is mentioned, organist of the Elche church of Saint Mary and its first known musical chapel maestro (between 1562 and 1594). \n\n
		The chapel maestro of the royal chapel of Madrid, Juan Bautista Comes (1582?&#8211;1643) was also linked to the music of the festa. According to the consueta of 1625, he composed a piece to replace the one the Holy Trinity sang. This piece was finally not included in the play and, although the above mentioned libretto contains the verses of the chant, the score has been lost. \n\n
		Nowadays, the chants in the Mystery &#8211; with the exception of the Araceli, which is accompanied with guitar and harp &#8211; are interpreted a cappella. We also know that a wind instrument – mostly a fagot&#8211; used to accompany some of the motets in the play, replacing the bass voice, as late as the first third of the 20th century. Besides, there are documents that prove the existence of an important chapel of players and singers in the church of Saint Mary of Elche, chapel that had its most outstanding epoch in the 18th century. Amongst those musicians, who were called in the consuetas “ministriles”, as they appeared in the Misteri, we could find players of different instruments, such as xeremia (like a flageolet), cornet, flute, oboe, sackbut, horn, violin, harp, etc., as well as professional singers who were sometimes hired in other cities. This professional musical chapel disappeared in 1835 and, in order to ensure the continuity of the representations of the Mystery, local amateur singers, following the great choral tradition of the village, took charge of its representation. \n\n
		In the present time, the assumptionist drama is represented by the members of the Chapel of the Mystery of Elche –formed by about sixty adults and thirty children. And, although none of them, except in some very occasional circumstances, is a professional singer, the quality of their voices and the magnificent blend they achieve can be enjoyed in the yearly representations of the drama and in the extraordinary concerts they offer. \n\n
	</string>

    <string name="info_tramoya_title">Scenaries</string>
    <string name="info_tramoya_subtitle">The Basilica of Santa María</string>
    <string name="info_tramoya_longtext">The big stage of the Mystery of Elche is the Basilica of Santa Maria, a baroque temple, whose construction began in 1673 and ended in 1784, the scene itself is divided into two parts:. Horizontal or "terrestrial" and the vertical or "air ". \n\n The first consists of a platform or "cadafal" rises in the transept of the church. Their arrangement allows the viewer, according to medieval custom, can be mounted on all four sides .. This platform is the mayor temple gate by an inclined plane called corridor accessible. Along this corridor are three small altars. Garden of Gethsemane, Calvary and the Holy grave. \n\n The air scenery or vertical is set in the dome of the church. It symbolizes the sky. Hidden on the canvas for the dome, from the perspective of the audience, there is a small wooden board. Allows stages all operations and work necessary to lower and raise the flying machine with the sign of the heavenly world. \n\n Such devices are three: the cloud or Granada in the descending angel announcing to Mary her death; the Recèlica or Araceli, occupied by five angels, three adults and two children, in the second part, the Assumption of the Virgin; similar, but smaller, by one adult and two children set out and the coronation or Trinidad, Araceli to be occupied the Holy Trinity. These three devices bound driven set up and down with thick ropes by two manual lathes on the terraces of the Church. \n\n The singers who do not descend from heaven will be marked outside the temple, originally in the hermitage of San Sebastián and currently in the adjacent Casa De La Festa. From this hermitage drive of singers and the authorities at the beginning of the presentation in a small procession, so that the streets become the stage of Festa. Scenario is extended to all the old medieval core than in the morning of August 15, with the Procesion&#8211;Burial of María.\n\n</string>
        
    <string name="info_celebration_title">Festivity</string>
    <string name="info_celebration_subtitle">The Misteri lived by the city</string>
    <string name="info_celebration_longtext">The Mystery of Elche is the only living example of the great celebrations devoted to the countries of the former Crown of Aragon spread to the Assumption of the Virgin Mary from the Middle Ages. The mystery is a festive celebration, an expression of faith, a dramatized catechesis, and above all, the most important festival of the city community, the quintessence of the Festa. \n\n The celebration consists of a number of different actions. In the first days of August, there are some preliminary actions such as voice test, where the work of children\'s voices can be selected, or angels test in which checks the proper functioning of air props and serenity of the little singer. The traditional festival begins on the evening of August 13, the so&#8211;called Night of Alba. This is a community event that ilicitanos on the rooftops of the city for an hour constantly rockets and fireworks brings ever, a range of light and sound to his patron. \n\n Between the two days of the traditional mystery, in the evening and early morning walks August 14 to 15, is another popular and festive event took place: the ROA. Thousands of elk with a burning candle in the streets of the city, where in the morning, spend the procession of the Virgin. And ended the day, 16&#8211;22 August develops his eighth. Before the image of the Virgin, recumbent again, Salves celebrated the Mother of God, with a solemn proclamation and sings a merry Assumptionists possibly seventeenth century. \n\n The popular devotion to the patron of the city is also manifested in various details, kept particularly large part in the festivities, including fairs, four clock in the morning of August 15, at the same Santa Maria cadafal. Also like in the clear interest of collecting fragments from the sky tinsel Santa Maria or some gold from the leaves of the palm down angels Granada, objects of devotion, which are stored as true relics.\n\n</string>
        
    <string name="info_recognition_title">Recognitions</string>
    <!--  string name="info_recognition_subtitle">-.-.- DE</string-->
    <string name="info_recognition_longtext">In recent years, the artistic values and traditional contents in the Misterio de Elche and its unique and exceptional character have been object of different recognitions and distinctions. The most outstanding are the following ones: \n\n · 1931: Declaration of National Monument by the Government of II the Spanish Republic \n · 1965: Declaration of Celebration of National Tourist Interest by the Ministry of Information and Tourism \n · 1980: Declaration of Celebration of International Tourist Interest by the Ministry of Information and Tourism \n · 1982: Plaque of Gold to the Tourist Merit by the Ministry of Transports, Tourism and Communications \n · 1982: Gold Medal of the Royal Academy of Fine Arts of San Carlos of Valencia \n · 1988: Sant Jordi’s Cross by the Generalitat of Catalonia \n · 1988: Necktie of the Order of Alfonso X El Sabio by the Ministry of Education and Science \n · 1990: Necktie of the Order of Isabel La Católica by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. \n · 1990: High Distinction of the Generalitat of Valencia \n · 1993: Gold Medal of the Royal Academy of Fine Arts of San Fernando of Madrid \n · 1997: Gold Medal of Bimillenary of the City by the City Council of Elche \n · 2001: Gold Medal of the Valencian Council of Culture \n · 2001: Declaration of Masterpiece of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Humanity by UNESCO \n · 2005: Knight (The Consultant President) of the Pontifical Order of San Silvestre.</string>
   
   	<!-- Menu option 4. buy tickets activities-->
   	<string name="buytickets">Buy tickets</string>

    <!-- Menu option 5. credits activities-->
    <string name="cred_title1">EXPLANATORY TEXTS</string>
    <string name="cred_title2">TRANSLATIONS</string>
    <string name="cred_title3">PHOTOGRAPHS</string>
    <string name="cred_title4">IDEA AND CONCEPT</string>
    <string name="cred_title5">PRODUCTION</string>
    <string name="cred_title6">DEVELOPMENT</string>
    <string name="cred_title7">ACCESSIBILITY</string>
    <string name="cred_title8">HOSTED BY</string>
    <string name="creditos">Information and Credits</string>
    <string name="seleccion_idioma">Language selection</string>
    <string name="live">Live</string>
</resources>